well welcome to another
living mana physical health tuesdays
today we're going to talk about stress
and exercise and what exercise can do
for you
so i don't have to tell you about what
type of a world that we live in now
where there is stress
there is fear
there is anxiety about what it is that's
going on we've got
the pandemic that we are still
sort of circling around in we have new
viruses on the horizon there is a
question about uh politics the stock
market
uh learning all of these sorts of things
what is it that is going on in all of
these things and how is it affecting our
bodies
so if we look back during the pandemic
okay so this is 2020. by late june of
2020 40 of adults in the united states
reported struggling with mental health
or substance abuse 31 percent had
anxiety depression symptoms 13 had
started or increased substance abuse
26 percent had trauma or stress related
disorders and 11 percent had seriously
considered suicide that's that's
according to the cdc
and
what is it
that
causes this
and what is the effect on the human body
we can only imagine
what it is well science is actually
giving us some insights into this and uh
it's it's actually quite interesting
we're finding out that
in the immune system the innate immune
system that's the part of the immune
system that goes around your body
looking for things to eat up
things that don't
resemble the human body things that are
pathogens or even
cellular damage okay so your cells that
are not acting appropriately and and may
be damaged these are things that could
lead to cancer
so
they're damaged and and they need to be
eaten up by the innate immune system
and
the thing that is responsible for that
as we mentioned is the innate immune
system and those are macrophages and uh
inflammation is what happens
when your immune system gets turned on
and starts doing that sort of stuff and
you start to feel heat you start to feel
pain redness swelling these are all
signs of inflammation and
there are things that are given off like
tumor necrosis factor alpha that is a
cytokine or a protein that is a signal
of inflammation in your body cytokines
and acute phase protein so this is all
what we know happens when there is an
infection or when there is tissue that
needs to be broken down it's part of the
innate immune system and inflammation is
what we see
so what happens why is this important
well dr jennifer heiss who is the
director of the fit lab at mcmaster
university in
ontario canada
said this recently
at the beginning of the pandemic about
anxiety
and worry
specifically about the pandemic she says
quote excessive anxiety about covet 19
can trigger
an immune response
that increases inflammation and readies
the immune system's equivalent of
special forces
known as inflammasomes that's right
inflammasomes
if sars cov2 acts like other viruses
then upon infection the inflammasomes
will be called to action to escalate the
inflammation even further so if you're
worried about getting an infection and
then you get the infection
it's even doubly as worse but too much
inflammation she says
does more harm than good it deregulates
immune function increasing our risk
of a viral infection
and this has been seen in a number of
studies this is one that was published
in 2017 it was kind of a review
looking at this
nlrp3 inflammasome this is exactly what
we were just talking about is this
structure that actually is the hub if
you will
of
inflammation and how it's actually tied
into mood in this case in clinical
depression here's another uh
story here the inflammasome pathways
linking psychological stress depression
and systemic illness and inside that
article it said according to this
hypothesis the inflammasome is a central
mediator by which
psychological and physical stressors can
contribute to the development of
depression as well as a bridge to
systemic disease
so they have seen and have studied in a
number of places as we have they are
listed where the inflammasome
has been linked to several autoimmune
conditions
autoimmune conditions are conditions
where the body the body's own innate
immune system and adaptive immune system
are attacking your own system so
diabetes type 1 type 2 inflammatory
bowel disease like crohn's disease like
ulcerative colitis
gaudy arthritis multiple sclerosis and
even vitiligo which is a discoloration
of the skin all of these things can be
related to inflammasome
pathology
but there was a article that came out
that i thought was really interesting in
may of 2019 just before the pandemic in
the journal of sport and health science
and it was titled the compelling link
between physical activity and the body's
defense mechanism
so this is really interesting
what they reviewed this is a review
article and let's go through the studies
that this article pulled out i think it
was really interesting there was a
number of studies and let's just sort of
go through them there was one that was
published by knee men at all where they
took 36 mildly obese sedentary women and
they randomized them to 15 weeks of
moderate intensity exercise that's about
45 minutes a day
for about five days a week walking a
program or
or similar versus an observational
control
so observational control they're not
doing the exercise
what did they find in those that did the
randomized
trial of moderate intensity so that's
about 45 minutes a day they had fewer
days with illness symptoms
than versus the controls and notice it
was
five days
of illness
for that given period of time versus
10.8 days of illness so basically less
than half of the illness days if they
were randomized so this is a randomized
controlled trial meaning that a lot of
confounders gets eliminated because
you're randomizing people to a group or
it's placebo
neiman all got excited about this and he
looked at now 91 obese women age 45
years of age plus or minus 1.1 years and
randomized them to a 12-week moderate
intensity program again 45 minutes a day
five days a week walking program
what did they find again fewer days with
illness symptoms
reported in the walkers versus the
controls
a couple of other studies chew back at
all randomized to one year this time
again
moderate intensity exercise about 45
minutes a day versus stretching control
and they found that illness incidents 30
percent in exercise
versus 48 in control so there's a
an absolute risk reduction of 18 percent
which means that you could just treat
five people with this and you would be
able to
completely eliminate it here in in one
person in the year
so a threefold decreased risk of illness
in the exercise group versus the control
in the final three months so in other
words it got better and better and
better as time went on finally here
barrett at all where they took 373 male
and female older adults is the biggest
one here on the page
randomize them to just eight weeks of
moderate intensity sustained exercise
and they noticed that there was a 14
reduction in illness a 23 reduction in
days of illness a 31 reduction in global
severity all of these compared to
controls now i want you to notice
something that's really important the
word moderate the word moderate the word
moderate and the word moderate
notice in all of these situations
they're not
asked to
go all out
to just really go until they couldn't go
at all this is very low level
moderate
exercise activity see the problem is a
lot of times when we talk about exercise
we in our mind
pull up the advertisements that we see
on instagram or on youtube or on the
television or we hear about we hear
about it's time to exercise we think
we've got to be
like these people that go to the gym
that don't really need to exercise
because they look really good
and i want to address that because
there's something known as the j curve
which we're going to talk about a lot in
this lecture
and this j curve describes exactly what
happens when you get off the couch and
start to actually do some exercise what
we see here are people who are sedentary
and that's here we're starting off at
normal and they are at zero in terms of
upper respiratory tract infections
although it could be just about anything
and then as you start to go and exercise
here to the right notice that there is a
reduction
in inflammation there is a reduction in
upper respiratory tract infections but
as you increase to heavy exertion
notice what happens the j-hook starts to
go back up and there could be a two to
six-fold increase
increase
in infection in inflammation and that's
the key that's the key that you need to
understand here is that when we talk
about exercise
we're not asking you to win a gold medal
at the olympics we're not asking you to
be the all-world champion we're asking
you to do enough exercise to reduce the
inflammation hopefully down to this area
right here which is the lowest
inflammatory point and the lowest level
of in this case upper respiratory tract
infections so you can get the majority
benefit and why do we say this well
because we've looked at studies we know
that moderate
short acute exercises mobilizes natural
killer cells it mobilizes cd8 highly
toxic cytotoxic lymphocytes
it causes stress hormones to remain
moderate and not high and all of this
over time enhances immunosurveillance
that means your immune system looking
for problems and lowers inflammation
it's particularly of benefit on people
who already have high levels of
inflammation as we'll talk about obese
and diseased individuals it can be an
immune system enhancer so if you are
concerned about
people in your area giving you a
specific infection and you know you're
going to go into a specific situation
where you might be at higher risk
doing a little bit of exercise leading
up to that might actually be beneficial
it can give you an enhanced antibody
response let's say you're about to get a
vaccination and you wanted to make sure
that your immune system is going to make
the most of a sneak peek at that antigen
well getting some exercise in would be a
good thing to do how about evidence of
summation effect over time modulating
tumeric genesis
atherosclerosis and other disease
processes again
moderate is the key word here short
acute exercise what happens when we do
heavy exercise
we get immune dysfunction inflammation
oxidative stress muscle damage
natural killer cells here
here immobilize them here we actually
get an increase in natural killer cells
neutrophils and tmb cell function and
many other measurements actually become
altered
okay altered for hours to days after
prolonged intensive exercise so the key
here is that you want to be doing
moderate exercise and not heavy exercise
if you want to get the most out of your
immune system
again further evidence of this here we
look at a walking bout which is a
moderate amount of exercise versus a
marathon race which is about 26 miles
so what happens here
we know in the
the dth or the delayed type
hypersensitivity response
there is a
significant reduction when you do a
marathon race okay
significant reduction but a specific
walking bout actually gives you a slight
increase same thing happens with
salivary iga which is something that you
want to have if you want to prevent
yourself from
getting pharyngeal spread of a virus
t-cell function is something that you
want to have you lose it with a marathon
race natural killer cell activity drops
significantly with marathon races
macrophage function granulocytes
oxidative bursts that's something that
you really want to have all of those
things drop
with marathon races all of them increase
slightly with moderate intensity
exercise so make sure that you're doing
that now the opposite is true here with
the neutrophyte neutrophil to lymphocyte
ratio cytokines and stress hormones
notice that there's a huge increase in
well there's an increase in both but
that increase is much larger in the
marathon racer because
there is more stress so yeah that is not
a good thing so if you think about it if
you're not on a professional baseball
team hockey team going to the olympics
you really have no basis
in terms of your immunity doing that
type of really strenuous exercise a lot
of people do marathon races and i think
they ought to be aware
of the risk that they're posing to their
body and their immune system when they
do those sorts of things how many times
have you heard of somebody in covet 19
dying and you found out that wow and
they were a
fill in the blank
professional athlete marathon runner
well they are actually
degrading their bodies when they are
actually causing and pushing their
bodies to that stress such to the point
that these teams that we see you know
people at the olympics the uh here we
have the hockey team we have track and
field they are all way out here
on this side and so as a result of that
they are particularly susceptible to
upper respiratory tract infections on
this graph but also increased
inflammation now what i thought was
really interesting
was i went out to the sports literature
to see what the experts say about this
because let's face it folks
when you are on the olympic team they
want you to go and get a gold medal for
their country that's what they're
funding you that's why they're giving
you a coach to train and you can be
absolutely assured that they're going to
get the best coaches that money can buy
and they're going to give you the best
advice that's going to make sure
that you bring home a gold medal so what
i did actually was i went out and i
accumulated all of the best evidence
from papers that had been published and
this is a summary of the most important
guidelines for elite athletes okay so
let's say you're
there's two types of people listening to
this or those who are couch potatoes and
who don't get up and exercise and i want
them to get up and exercise just a
little bit
but there's those of you out there who
go to the gym every day you have your
workout routine and right now you're
kind of freaking out a little bit right
you're saying wow am i doing too much
well here is the most important
guidelines for elite athletes to keep
their immune systems robust and illness
rates low
despite
physiological stress
experience and this is based on some of
the best and most recent research here
and i i put these here for anybody who
wants to learn more about it but i
called these and basically went through
them and found the best advice and here
it is that's listed so training and
competition load management what should
you do number one develop a detailed
individualized training and competition
plan that also provides for sufficient
recovery using guess what sleep
nutrition hydration and psychological
strategies number two use small
increments when changing the training
load typically less than 10 weekly so
you don't want to do too much too
quickly
number three develop a competition event
calendar that is based on the health of
the athlete so you don't want to over
stress yourself this is the key is when
you are pushing yourself that much and
going to the top of that j hook you
don't want to go too far
monitor for early signs and symptoms of
overreaching over training and illness
avoid intensive training when ill or
experiencing the early signs of symptoms
of illness
participate in ongoing illness
surveillance systems by sports agencies
all right what about hygienic lifestyle
nutritional and behavioral strategies
minimize pathogen exposure by avoiding
close contact with affected individuals
in crowded enclosed spaces and not
sharing drinking or eating implements
avoid exercise sessions in poorly
ventilated clubs and gymnasium
facilities the medical staff should
isolate infected athletes
check all right limit hand to face
contact so you really want to limit the
your chances of getting infected from
somebody nearby so wash hands limit hand
to face contact
and the medical staff should educate
athletes to minimize pathogen spread to
others so that's talking about sneezing
coughing
dare i even say masks here in some
situations when you can't avoid it
follow other hygienic practices to limit
all types of infections including they
say here in the recommendation safe sex
and the use of condoms wearing open
footwear when using
public facilities to limit skin
infections inspecting or using insect
repellents that's important because
malaria can spread through mosquitoes
and covering the arms and legs and
clothing at dawn or dusk so
they're showing here that there are
certain behaviors that are risky and
here they recommend safe sex
of course abstinence is also very good
and also prevents you from getting
illnesses and diseases that way as well
probably more
appropriate even than a safe sex so
hygienic lifestyle nutritional and
behavioral strategies
maintain vaccines needed for home and
foreign travel with a focus on annual
influenza vaccination
follow strategies that facilitate
regular high quality sleep avoid
excessive alcohol intake i would say
that
studies have shown that any alcohol
intake is excessive
and then finally consume a well-balanced
diet with sufficient energy to maintain
a healthy weight with a focus on grains
fruits and vegetables to provide
sufficient
carbohydrates
and polyphenols that reduce
exercise-induced inflammation and
improved viral protection notice here
this is not talking about a low
carbohydrate diet we'll talk about this
later but actually carbohydrates can be
very
helpful especially if they also contain
polyphenols we'll talk more about that
and then finally follow stress
management techniques that decrease
extraneous load of life hassles and
stresses develop coping strategies that
minimize the internalized impact of
negative life events and emotions and
periodically monitor psychological
stresses using available instruments
and it's again because they're way up
here on the j curve hook all right
obesity so what does obesity do notice
that obesity is basically a way of
increasing inflammation
and so if you have inflammation this is
something that you're going to want to
avoid
is avoiding obesity because there are
reactive oxygen species okay how do you
do that
well exercise and eating healthy
what about post exercise after you
exercise there's some data and this is
what they go into here
that after
intense exercise
training
that eating
fruits such as bananas with water is
actually associated with a higher plasma
glucose and insulin levels and lower
plasma stress hormones and that's
important because what happens is it
reduces inflammation so that's something
that you may want to consider if you are
exercising quite a bit is acute
carbohydrate ingestion right after you
exercise and then we talked about
polyphenols look at all this color here
this is just amazing stuff a high
proportion of ingested polyphenols from
fruits
vegetables and other plant foods passed
through the small intestine unabsorbed
and reached the colon
where bacterial degradation promotes
smaller phenolics that can be absorbed
into circulation after going phase two
conjugation in the liver so in other
words
things that you can absorb on your own
are digested by bacteria they get broken
down into smaller things that get
absorbed go to the blood go to the liver
and things get put on them and these are
very important to athletes including
anti-inflammatory antiviral
anti-oxidative and immune cell signaling
effects so this is really important
these polyphenols things that are very
colorful
okay
good so we've talked about stress
fair anxiety and
how you can reduce those because these
things can induce inflammation and we've
just talked about how exercise
if it's done appropriately can actually
reduce
inflammation but let's talk more about
depression
stress and fear
and for that i want to talk really
quickly about this study that was done
by our friend dr jennifer heiss out of
the fit lab in mcmaster university in
ontario canada so she works on a college
campus and
students towards the end of the term get
very anxious because of their exams and
some can even get depressed as we'll see
so she looked at 61 university students
for six weeks in fact it was the last
six weeks of the term 72 of them were
female she divided them into three
groups number one those that did not
exercise number two
those that exercised three times a week
but did it moderately and those that
exercised three times a week and did it
highly intense
okay so
in both exercising groups they did it
for six weeks three times a week monday
wednesday friday in the moderate
intensity exercise they only went about
84 watts about 20 minutes a day those in
the high intensity did 155 watts of
workout
only about 20 minutes a day those in the
moderate got our their heart rates up
into the 140s those in the high
intensity up to 174. those are you who
are familiar with the borg scale 11 out
of 20 for the moderate 15 out of 20 for
the high intensity this is basically
telling them how short of breath they
were okay so what did she do
she measured a bunch of things she
measured how depressed they were she
measured enzymes she measured
inflammation let's take a look
so the first thing that i want you to
notice is the beck depression inventory
scale this is basically a validated way
of measuring how depressed people are
and notice that from the beginning of
the six weeks to the end of the six
weeks those that did no exercise had a
significant increase in their depression
and no surprise i mean they're under a
lot of stress they have tests this is
going to
determine their career potentially
notice though that those that did
moderate and intense exercise not only
did not get more depressed they actually
got less depressed but the moderate
intensity got more less depressed okay
they actually became much more less
depressed
what about anxiety not a huge difference
there again the modern intensity came
out on top and perceived stress notice
that those that exercise more vigorously
actually had a higher perceived stress
than those that exercised moderately
again going along with what we talked
about this j-hook now if we looked at
tumor necrosis factor alpha which we
talked about at the beginning that is a
inflammatory cytokine the huge
difference there between those that did
not do moderate intensity exercise and
those that did also we saw the same
thing for il-6 which is also a cytokine
as well so all of this caused dr heiss
to conclude that a critical question we
sought to address was whether different
physical exercise programs that prevent
the development of these depressive
symptoms also reduce pro-inflammatory
cytokines indeed we found support for
this six weeks of moderate intensity
continuous exercise which resulted in
less depression and i think that's the
key here if we look at a number of
studies
this one was done in 2016 with almost a
thousand participants when they looked
at depression versus no intervention
exercise had a large impact on that
let's face it exercise can improve mood
almost immediately it can help you lose
weight which can reduce inflammation and
exercise has very few side effects
here's another study a systematic review
that was done back in 2019 we looked at
24 studies in this subject almost 80 000
subjects in this study
versus people with exercise there was a
13 reduction in those with moderate
exercise with elevated anxiety symptoms
a 34 reduction in
any general anxiety disorder and 46
reduction in generalized anxiety
disorder specifically
there's another study that was done this
time in
july of 2021
looked at 35 women with ptsd and they
looked at
this study whether or not exercise in
relation to a shock or a post-traumatic
event would prevent them from getting
post-traumatic stress disorder and the
answer was yes
exercise
in a situation that could lead to
post-traumatic stress disorder was more
likely to prevent post-traumatic stress
disorder
than
than if you did not do it again this
j-hook we're not asking you to go run a
marathon we're asking you to get off the
couch start to do a little bit of
walking start to walk around your house
go outside
do something small and there'll be some
benefits let's talk really quickly about
what specifically we ought to do
depending on who you are preschool age
children three to five years of age
just be active throughout the day do a
bunch of diverse things it's great what
about six to 17 year olds
they should be getting 60 minutes of
moderate to vigorous exercise every day
that's why they have recess that's why
they have physical education three times
a week should have aerobic muscle
strengthening bone strengthening stuff
okay what about adults
after high school okay move and sit less
during the day it's really easy to do
that because we have jobs that we've got
to do any kind of activity is beneficial
you should be getting 150 to 300 minutes
a week okay that's about 20 to 40
minutes a day of moderate intensity for
best okay muscle strengthening you can
do that about two days a week so going
to the gym lifting weights doing in your
own house that's great what about older
adults people who are retired it's the
same as for adults except you should
probably add some balance training to
that we don't want to have fall so so
practice your balancing and you might
need to make some adjustments based on
some disabilities what about women
during pregnancy again 20 minutes a day
you don't need to decrease a prior
routine that you have been doing
although you may want to consult with
your obstetrician to make sure you don't
have any specific things obviously if
you have bed rest you got to stay on
your bed okay and what about adults with
chronic health conditions or
disabilities again 20 to 40 minutes a
day muscle strengthening two times a
week consult with a physician if there
are any limitations
so we've seen a lot of evidence that
shows that exercise really
can have a lot of wonderful effects i
mean it can improve your mood
it's shown that you can improve your
metabolism it can reduce inflammation if
you're depressed it can reduce
depression it can reduce perceived
stress and it can reduce the cytokines
that you see
floating around
in your system so
again we don't want to have too much
exercise because that can actually
increase things toward the end remember
that j-hook that we were talking about
so for those of you who are
you kind of know where you are right you
kind of know are you towards the
beginning of that j-hook or are you
towards the end of that j-hook if you're
towards the end of that j-hook and
you're really committed to exercising a
lot make sure you're taking precautions
so that you don't over-exert yourself
but i think the majority of us are in
that early stage they're in the early
portion of that j-hook and what we
really need to start doing is getting
outside getting some fresh air getting
some sunlight and getting some exercise
you know we've talked about these things
individually we've talked about
sunshine we've talked about light
but you know there's something about
getting outside and walking around and
getting that exercise maybe even doing
something like we showed in the slide
maybe some gardening you're actually
getting the benefit of all of these
things all at the same time so getting
outside gives you fresh air maybe you're
breathing in some of the perfumes of the
of the flowers or the trees you're
getting some near infrared radiation
like we've talked about before you're
getting sunlight to your eyes
but you're also getting exercise and
exercise is a great way of reducing
inflammation and also
helping with your mood and imagine that
exercise and mood together with sunlight
is going to have a tremendous impact
with your overall mental health and
physical health and that's exactly what
we aim to do here so thanks for joining
us
ask us some questions go ahead and
email those to us
and i can't wait to see you again on our
physical health tuesdays here
at the living mana church